Claire Falkenstein
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Claire Falkenstein papers
circa 1914-1997, bulk 1940-1990
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Falkenstein, Claire
42.8 linear feet
The papers of sculptor, painter, jewelry designer, and teacher Claire Falkenstein measure 42.8 linear feet and date from 1917 to her death in 1997. There is extensive correspondence with fellow artists, collectors, critics, friends, museums, and galleries. The collection also contains biographical materials, much of it collected and organized by Falkenstein, personal and business records, writings, diaries, exhibition files, commission files, teaching files, photographs, original artwork, scrapbooks, and printed materials. There is a short motion picture film of an interview with Falkenstein featuring the windows she designed for St. Basil's Church in Los Angeles.
Provenance
The Claire Falkenstein papers were donated in 1997 by Steffan Wacholtz and Nancy Kendall, trustees for the Claire Falkenstein Trust.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art also holds two oral history interviews with Claire Falkenstein. The interview on April 13, 1965 was conducted by Betty Hoag and the one on March 2 and 21, 1995 was conducted by Paul Karlstrom.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Claire Falkenstein (1908-1997) spent the majority of her life working as an artist, sculptor, jewelry designer, teacher, and writer in California.
Claire Falkenstein was born in 1908 and grew up in Coos Bay, Oregon. In 1920, Falkenstein and her family moved to Berkeley, California, where she attended high school and then college at the University of California at Berkeley, studying philosophy, anthropology, and art. She graduated in 1930. Falkenstein had her first solo show at the East-West Gallery in San Francisco in 1930, the only member of her class to have an exhibition before graduation.
During the early 1930s, Falkenstein studied at Mills College with modernist sculptor Alexander Archipenko. There she also met Bauhaus artists Laszlo Moholy-Nagy and Gyorgy Kepes. Falkenstein married her high school sweetheart, Richard McCarthy in 1936.
In 1944, Falkenstein had her first New York exhibition at the Bonestall Gallery. At that time, Falkenstein's primary mediums were stone and wood. However, she became increasingly experimental with new materials that included sheet aluminum, Cor-Ten steel, glass, plastics, and welded wire rods while maintaining a connection to organic and natural forms. Her work in jewelry design was an outlet for exploring these new materials, forms, and techniques on a small scale. As her work grew physically larger, so did her recognition and it was her work in sculpture that won her a faculty appointment at the California School of Fine Arts from 1947-1949. It was here that she met Patricia and Clyfford Still, Hassel Smith, and Richard Diebenkorn.
In 1948, Falkenstein was invited to exhibit at the Salon des Realites Nouvelle in Paris, her first European show. She eventually moved to Europe in 1950 and had studios in Paris, Venice, and Rome. While in Europe, Falkenstein executed a number of large scale commissions, including the stair screen for Galerie Stadler (1955), grotto gates for Princess Pignatelli's villa in Rome (1957), and the bronze, steel, and the glass gate at the Peggy Guggenheim Museum in Venice (1961). While in Paris, she became acquainted with noted art critic Michel Tapie, with whom she maintained a life-long friendship.
During the 1940s and 1950s Falkenstein was a regular contributor to Arts and Architecture magazine, most often writing the "Art Comments from San Francisco" section. While in Paris, she also wrote a column on art news for the New York Herald Tribune.
Falkenstein returned to the United States in 1962, eventually renovating a studio space in Venice, California. It was here that she conceived her largest commissions. In 1965, Falkenstein received a commission from the California Savings and Loan to create a sculpture for a large fountain at the front of the bank in downtown Los Angeles. The copper tube fountain, entitled "Structure and Flow #2," was the first of many large scale public art commissions that Falkenstein completed during her years in California. Her most important commission in the United States, completed in 1969, was for the doors, rectory gates and grills and stained-glass windows for St. Basil's Church on Wilshire Boulevard in Los Angeles. The eight doors and fifteen rectory screens, including 80 foot high windows in the nave, were an expansion of the "never ending screen" concept that Falkenstein executed with the Pignatelli commission in Rome. She continued to use this motif in her work throughout her career.
Claire Falkenstein worked as an arts instructor, visiting artist, and guest lecturer at many colleges, workshops, and schools in California. Her first position was at Mills College from 1946-1947. Shortly thereafter, she was appointed to the faculty at the California School of Fine Arts and later taught in the Extension Divisions of the University of California, Berkeley. She taught classes at California State Polytechnic University, California State University at Davis, and the Anna Head School. Falkenstein also taught art at the Pond Farm Workshops in California, and lectured at numerous colleges and museums. She served on many juried art shows in Southern California.
Falkenstein was acquainted with many artists, writers, instructors, collectors, gallery owners, and critics. Close friends included Esther and Bob Robles, Clyfford and Patricia Still, Michel Tapie, Allan Temko, Mark Tobey, Frans Wildenhain, and other notable figures in the art world.
Falkenstein continued to complete large scale private and public commissioned sculptures during the 1960s through the 1980s, including work for the University of Southern California, Hyland Biological Laboratory, California State University at Dominquez Hills and the California State Department of Motor Vehicles. Throughout her career, Falkenstein's work was featured in numerous exhibitions across the country. Her sculpture and other artwork can be found in the permanent collections of the Museum of Modern Art, Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, Smithsonian American Art Museum, Coos Art Museum, Harvard University Art Museum, University of Southern California Fisher Museum of Art, Los Angeles County Museum of Art, and the Tate Gallery.
Falkenstein died in 1997 at the age of 89.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor, painter, jewelry designer, and teacher Claire Falkenstein measure 42.8 linear feet and date from 1917 to her death in 1997. There is extensive correspondence with fellow artists, collectors, critics, friends, museums, and galleries. The collection also contains biographical materials, much of it collected and organized by Falkenstein, personal and business records, writings, diaries, exhibition files, commission files, teaching files, photographs, original artwork, scrapbooks, and printed materials. There is a short motion picture film of an interview with Falkenstein featuring the windows she designed for St. Basil's Church in Los Angeles.
Biographical material includes appointment calendars, awards and honorary degrees, interview transcripts, passports, resumes, wills, and scrapbooks. Scrapbooks were compiled by Falkenstein and focus primarily on her exhibitions at the Galerie Stadler and Gallery Meyer in 1959 and 1960. Also of interest are the "biography files" created and arranged by Falkenstein. These files contain material that she personally felt was the most important in documenting her activities each year. They include correspondence, exhibition catalogs, printed material, and invitations.
Measuring nine linear feet, correspondence is extensive and comprehensively documents Falkenstein's work, social life, relationships, and other business and personal activities. Correspondence dates from 1941 to 1997 and includes business letters and correspondence with friends and family. Her communications with friends, family, clients, gallery owners, collectors, museums, publishers, foundations, and grant agencies reveal many of her ideas and techniques. Individual correspondents include Ray Green, Peggy Guggenheim, Katherine Kuh, May O'Donnell, Ken Sawyer, Clyfford and Pat Still, Michel Tapie, Allan Temko, Mark Tobey, and Frans Wildenhain. Gallery and museum correspondence is with the San Francisco Museum of Art, Coos Art Museum, Los Angeles Museum of Art, Galerie Stadler (Paris), Gallery Mayer (Paris), Malvina Miller (New York), Martha Jackson Gallery (New York), Jack Rutberg Fine Arts (Los Angeles), Galerie Anderson-Mayer (Paris), and Bolles Gallery. Correspondence is also found in the Commission Files and Exhibition Files.
Personal and business records contain a wide variety of material documenting Falkenstein's business, financial, legal, professional, and personal transactions. Files are found for sales and prices, art inventories, smaller jewelry commissions, her work as a juror, her business with galleries, legal affairs and contracts, expenses, records of arts organizations to which she belonged, conferences, grants and fellowships, studio and house renovations, her Paris studio and Paris expenses, travel, donations, loans and consignments, conservation, art shipping, insurance, and taxes. Oversized visitor's logs contain comments from visitors to Falkenstein's studio in Venice, California.
Falkenstein maintained comprehensive documentation of her exhibitions from her first exhibition in the 1930s to the last one at the Merging One Gallery in 1996. Files include both a chronological record and individual record for nearly all of her exhibitions. Found with the files are correspondence, photographs, loan and shipping records, catalogs, announcements, clippings, articles, and other records. Most of the photographs related to exhibitions are found in the Photographs Series. The files for exhibitions at the Fresno Art Museum, Martha Jackson Gallery and Jack Rutberg Fine Art Gallery are particularly rich.
Commission files document nearly all of Falkenstein's public and private large-scale projects and often contain a visual record of the work, as well as correspondence, design notes, contracts, and expense reports. There is documentation of the St. Basils Church windows in Los Angeles; the Peggy Guggenheim gate in Venice, Italy; and the fountain at the California Savings and Loan, in Los Angeles; and many others. There is also a chronological record of her commissions. The bulk of the photographs of commissions are found in the Photograph series. Also, most of Falkenstein's jewelry design commissions are found in the Personal and Business Records series.
Falkenstein's work as a prolific writer, particularly in the 1940s and 1950s, is well-documented here through her numerous published articles in Arts and Architecture magazine, and the New York Herald-Tribune. Her work for Arts and Architecture was primarily written for the "Art Comments from San Francisco" section. She was living in Paris when she contributed an art news column to the New York Herald-Tribune. Also found here are five diaries and one journal dating from circa 1929-1978. The entries are inconsistent and concern mostly travel. The diaries from 1929 and 1934 are more personal. Falkenstein also maintained extensive notes and notebooks about artwork ideas, observations about art, research, and even drafts of letters. There are also many notes about various topics, including art and class notes. Additional writings are eclectic and cover a wide range of topics, including music, poetry, the script for Falkestein's film entitled Touching the Quick, and drafts of her unpublished book on murals. A handful of writings by others are found, most with annotations by Falkenstein.
Teaching files include Falkenstein's numerous lectures given while teaching at Mills College, Pond Farm Workshops, and California School of Fine Arts, and various symposiums and conferences. Also found are lesson plans, contracts, scattered correspondence, and notes. The files on her tenure at the Pond Farm Workshops are particularly interesting, with notes about her fellow teacher Frans Wildenhain and correspondence with workshop owners, Jane and Gordon Herr.
There are extensive photographs of Falkenstein, her family and friends, colleagues, commissions, exhibitions, and works of art. Included are many images of Falkenstein, of Falkenstien with her art, of Falkentstien working, and of Falkenstein's studio. There are numerous photographs of Falkenstein with friends, family, and colleagues in social or work settings. Also found are photographs of exhibition openings, installation views, and works of art exhibited. Additional photographs document Falkenstein's commissions, including images of her at work. Additional images of commissions may also be found in the Commission Series, but the bulk are filed here. There are numerous photographs of Falkenstein's works of art, including drawings, sculpture, jewelry, murals, lamps, and ceramics.
Falkenstein's papers include a large amount of sketches, sketchbooks, and drawings. Many of the sketches and drawings relate to her ideas about commissions and large sculpture, jewelry designs, and general sketches. Sketches are also found in the Commission Files. Also included are drawings by Mark Tobey and Michel Tapie, and others.
Finally, printed materials include general exhibition catalogs, newspapers clippings, and clippings of articles by and about Falkenstein. Also included are books that have been inscribed and signed by the author.
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
University of California, San Francisco--School of Fine Arts--Faculty; Mills College--Faculty; Fresno Art Museum; Merging One Gallery; Pond Farm Workshop
Subjects-Topical:
Women artists--California; Women artists--France--Paris; Sculptors--California; Sculptors--France--Paris; Painters--California; Jewelry--Design; Educators--California; Designers--California; Art--Study and teaching; Art patronage; Art--Economic aspects; Artists' studios
Types of Materials:
Drawings; Photographs--aat; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks--aat; Motion pictures (visual works)--aat; Diaries--aat; Articles; Transcripts; Awards; Interviews; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Drafts (documents); Poetry; Notebooks; Travel journals; Scripts
Names:
Green, Ray, 1908-1997; Guggenheim, Peggy, 1898; Kuh, Katharine; O'Donnell, May, 1906-2004; Sawyer, Kenneth B.; Still, Clyfford, 1904-; Still, Patricia; Tapie, Michel; Temko, Allan; Tobey, Mark; Wildenhain, Frans, 1905; Coos Art Museum; Galerie Anderson-Mayer; Gallery Stadler; Jack Rutberg Fine Arts (Los Angeles, Calif.); John Bolles Gallery (San Francisco, Calif.); Los Angeles Museum of Art; Malvina Miller; Martha Jackson Gallery; San Francisco Museum of Art
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1934-1997 (Box 1-4, 41; 4.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1931-1997 (Box 5-13; 9 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal and Business Records, 1936-1997 (Box 14-17, 41, 46-49; 4.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Exhibitions, 1930-1996 (Box 18-21, 42, OV 50; 3.3 linear feet)
Series 5. Commissions, 1930-1992 (Box 21-22, OV 50-54; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 6: Writings, circa 1929-1993 (Box 22-26, 42, 55; 4.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Teaching Files, 1929-1995 (Box 26; .8 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1917-1997 (Box 27-35, 43, 55-56; 9.5 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, circa 1937-1995 (Box 36-37, 44, 57; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 10: Printed Materials, circa 1914-1990 (Box 37-40, 45, 58; 3.9 linear feet)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, 1934-1997, Series 1:; (Box 1-4, 41; 4.3 linear ft.)
  Biographical files include resumes, interviews, address books, awards, calendars, legal and travel documents, scrapbooks, and additional "biography files" compiled by Falkenstein. While other series provide specific information about Falkenstein's life and career, material in this series offers users a good overview of the highlights of her career as an artist and teacher.
  Biographical Materials are arranged into three subseries:
  1.1: General Biographical Files, 1934-1997
  1.2: Scrapbooks, 1943-1982
  1.3: "Biography Files," 1943-1982
  - General Biographical Files, 1934-1997, 1.1:
    This subseries contains awards, honorary degrees, interviews, passports, resumes, appointment calendars, and address books. The appointment calendars, resumes, and interviews document Falkenstein's busy schedule and focus on making her art accessible to the public. The short interview on motion picture film is particularly interesting as she talks about her ideas for the window design at St. Basil's Church.
    The files are arranged alphabetically by type of material and then chronologically by date.
    - Address Books, circa 1951-1959, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Address Book, A-I, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Address Book, J-Z, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Address Books, circa 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Appointment Calendars, 1942, 1948-1973, (10 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-15)
    - Appointment Calendars, 1974-1995, (14 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-14)
    - Appointment Calendars, 1996-1997, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Articles about Falkenstein, 1969-1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Awards, 1943, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Awards, 1931-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Awards, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Awards, circa 1990-1996, (Oversized item in Box 41) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Award - American Institute of Decorators, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Award - Los Angeles Times Women of the Year, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Awards - Design in Steel Award Program, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Awards - California Art Education Association Honoree, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Awards - Outstanding Alumna Award at The Head-Royce School, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Birth Certificate - Delayed, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Genealogy Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Honorary Degree from Utah State University, 1990, (Oversized awards housed in Box 41) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Interview with Falkenstein, Mark Tobey, Michel Tapie, and Yvonne Hagen, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Motion Picture Film, Interview with Falkenstein on Design of St. Basils Church Windows, circa 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Interview with Falkenstein, conducted by Laura Byerly, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Interview in Currant Art Magazine, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Interview with Falkenstein, conducted by Becky McKane, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Interview with Falkenstein for UCLA Oral History Program, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Interview with Falkenstein, circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Interview with Falkenstein at Escalen Institute in California, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Material on Falkenstein for Planned Biography, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Narrative Biography for Guggenheim Foundation Fellowship, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Passports, 1956-1958, 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Passports, 1974-1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Resume, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Resumes, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Resumes, circa 1962-1982 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Resumes, circa 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Travel Documents, 1950-1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Vaccination Certificates, 1950, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Wedding Announcements for Falkenstein and Richard McCarthy, circa 1934 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Wills, 1985, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Oversized Awards - Utah State University Honorary Degree, 1990, (From Box 3, F. 15) (Box 41)
  - Scrapbooks, 1950-1989, 1.2:
    Falkenstein compiled scrapbooks covering a wide range of her activities, including career highlights, specific exhibitions, writings, ideas and inspirations, and travel. They contain exhibition catalogs, reviews, articles, photographs, invitations, and congratulatory letters. The exhibition scrapbooks are particularly complete and the Galerie Stadler and Gallery Meyer scrapbooks include numerous photographs of the exhibition openings. The scrapbook on artwork ideas contains photographs, short descriptions, clippings, and rough sketches for future projects.
    Scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order; oversized scrapbooks are housed separately.
    - Career Highlights Scrapbook, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Travels in Europe Scrapbook 1954 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Falkenstein's Articles in New York Herald Tribune, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Scrapbook on Galerie Stadler Exhibition, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Exhibitions Scrapbook, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Scrapbook on Gallery Meyer Exhibition, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook on Gallery Meyer Exhibition, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook on Galerie Stadler Exhibition, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Career Highlights Scrapbook, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Career Highlights Scrapbook, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook of Falkenstein's Artwork Ideas and Inspirations, 1961-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Oversized Scrapbook on Bolles Gallery Exhibition in San Francisco, 1958 (Box 41)
    - Oversized Scrapbook on Exhibitions and Commissions, 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    - Oversized Scrapbook on Exhibitions, 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    - Oversized Scrapbook, 1963 (Box 41)
  - Biography Files, 1943-1982, 1.3:
    This subseries consists of "biography files" created and arranged by Falkenstein. The files document activities and projects that she felt best reflected her career accomplishments. They highlight exhibitions, commissions, teaching and lectures, writings for art journals, and grant awards. Of particular interest are the press reviews for Falkenstein's public commissions and exhibitions.
    These files are arranged in chronological order.
    - 1943-1959, (15 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-21)
    - 1964-1968, (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 22-26)
    - 1971-1975, (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 27-31)
    - 1977-1982, (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 32-37)
- Correspondence, 1931-1997, Series 2:; (Box 5-13; 9 linear feet)
  There is extensive correspondence with friends, family, galleries, clients, museums, collectors, and writers. The files contain original incoming correspondence and duplicate copies of outgoing correspondence, some with several drafts. Correspondence concerns many family, personal, and art-related topics and work, including upcoming exhibitions, commissions, art news, and her life and work in Paris. Correspondence with family members includes her husband Richard McCarthy and sister Helen Bickle. Correspondence with her husband offers details about her life in Paris from 1951 to 1960. Correspondence with her friend Myrtle Wolf is particularly extensive. Some letters contain enclosures, such as photographs, clippings, and nnouncements. Correspondence with clients, for both public and private commissions, may also include contracts, invoices, and expense reports, and should be consulted with the commission files which also contain correspondence. Additional correspondence is also found in the personal and business records series and the exhibitions series.
  Additional named correspondents include Carla Accardi, Jean Arp, Anne Baxter, Jae Carmichael, Olive Cowell, Zoe Dusanne, Garrett Eckbo, Sam Francis, Ray Green, Peggy Guggenheim, Katherine Kuh, Frank Lobdell, Sybil Moholy-Nagy, Grace Morley, Berto Morucchio, May O'Donnell, Joanna and Gifford Philips, Ken Sawyer, Gertrude Shurr, Darthea Spayer, Clyfford and Pat Still, Michel Tapie, Antonio Tapies, Allan Temko, Mark Tobey, June Wayne, Wilhelm Wessel, Frans Wildenhain, among many others.